Okay boker tov. Today's daf is דף נ"א Daf Nun Aleph and
we're continuing the whole discussion about learning out that the four applications
of the blood of the חטאת chatas are מעכב, me'akev, like are
all necessary, and then also the of the חטאת הפנימית, chatat hapnimit,
thank you, of the inner חטאת, chatat, and also the seven applications
that are done on the פרוכת, parochet, and then applying that to
יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, and applying that to the goats of עבודה
זרה, avoda zara, all of these inner
חטאות. chatatot. I think what I here I just circled this because
I forgot to mention yesterday while I was doing it that the
that, you know, when we're talking about the ways in which the
פר par and the goats of יום כיפור Yom Kippur are different,
in addition to the fact that they've got the what do you
call it? That they have the כפורת kaporet here that you have
it on the top of the on the top of the on
the, you know, the cover of the ארון, aron, the seven plus
one, the פרוכת parochet is the same that it's seven plus one,
but well the seven is the same but the plus one is
actually different normal there's just seven, and the other thing that's different
here is the seven on the roof of the מזבח. mizbeach. So
a normal חטאת chatas has seven on the פרוכת parochet and four
on the horns, an inner חטאת, chatas, and this has seven plus
one, seven plus one, seven on the roof, etc. Anyway, okay, so
that's the various things that we were learning out, and one of
the recent things that we were learning out was the issue of
this word
of oh this whole thing that לפר Lapar here comes to teach
that the same הלכות halachot apply by יום כיפור. Yom Kippur. And
that same הלכות halachot would be like that all of these applications
are מעכב, me'akev, or the same הלכות halachot might be like that
this אצבע בדם וטבילה, etzba b'dam u'tvila, these special things about how
the dipping is done and so on, and that was, you know,
that was one position to learn it out from the word פר,
par, and then you had a very weird קל וחומר kal v'chomer
of Rabbi Ishmael, I think it was Rabbi Ishmael, who basically said,
"Well, you know, since there's some overlap here and here between this
ox and this goat, this cow and this goat, so then this
cow and this cow certainly there's going to be an overlap and
certainly that's going to tell us to apply all the stuff that
we don't know yet." So anyway, so that was some very strange
קל וחומר. kal v'chomer. Anyway, let's move on. So that's sort of
where we left off. So the גמרא Gemara says like this: אמר
רב פפא: Amar Rav Papa: קסבר תנא דבי Kasavar Tana d'vei we
just did. Okay, לפר זה פר העלם דבר של ציבור. Lapar zeh
par helam davar shel tzibbur. Okay, now the other thing therefore they
said is is that if לפר lapar was not coming to teach
that these things like אצבע בדם וטבילה, etzba b'dam u'tvila, whatever it
is, applies by the יום כיפור Yom Kippur thing, if that's not
what it was coming to do, what do you do with this
word לפר? lapar? So what Rabbi Ishmael says you do with this
word לפר lapar is לפר lapar is coming to tell me, "Oh,
this ox, פר העלם דבר של ציבור." par helam davar shel tzibbur.
It's like, "Wait, why do you need it to tell me this
ox? We're talking about this ox." And the למד lamed is coming
to tell me פר כהן משיח. par kohen mashiach. So for Rabbi
Ishmael, the פר לפר par lapar here is not coming to teach
to יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, it's coming to somehow merge these two
or link these two. But for what purpose? So that's what the
גמרא's Gemara going to ask. Okay? So okay. לפר זה פר העלם
דבר של ציבור. Lapar zeh par helam davar shel tzibbur. הציבור גופיה
כתיב! Habtzibbur gufei ksiv! What do you mean? Oh, this comes to
include the פר העלם דבר של ציבור. par helam davar shel tzibbur.
Yeah, that's what we're talking about, that's the context. So אמר רב
פפא: Amar Rav Papa: משום דבעי גמורי פר העלם דבר של ציבור
ביותרת ושתי הכליות לשעירי עבודה כוכבים. Mishum d'ba'aya gmurei par helam davar
shel tzibbur biyoteret v'shtei haklayot l'se'irei avoda kochavim. Okay, 'cause here one
of the things that we want to now do is say that
the idea that you need the lobe of the liver and the
two kidneys and that's part of the אימורים emurim that's offered on
the מזבח, mizbeach, so that's not written here, it's only written by
the פר כהן משיח, par kohen mashiach, that's what that's written. So
another thing that's only written up here, ויותרת viyoteret plus השתי כליות
hashtei haklayot that's part of what's offered up as the as the
אימורים, emurim, okay, and we want to apply that הלכה halacha over
here to שעירי עבודה זרה. se'irei avoda zara. All right? So how
are we going to get it to apply to שעירי עבודה זרה?
se'irei avoda zara? So let's take a look. The basic way we're
going to get it to apply is through somehow פר העלם דבר
של ציבור. par helam davar shel tzibbur. But you can't as we
just taught yesterday, if you learn something through one derivation you can't
then go and like turn it over and apply it somewhere else,
so we have to somehow implicitly get this as if it's written
down here, and if it's as if it's written down here that's
going to allow us to then teach to the goat of עבודה
זרה. avoda zara. All very complicated.
The אימורים emurim on the מזבח. mizbeach.
Yeah, but it never mentioned, yeah, but it never specifically mentioned those
two in the other context.
So אמר רב פפא: Amar Rav Papa: משום דבעי גמורי פר העלם
דבר של ציבור ביותרת ושתי הכליות. Mishum d'ba'aya gmurei par helam davar
shel tzibbur biyoteret v'shtei haklayot. We want this to teach that the
inner חטאת chatas of עבודה זרה avoda zara also has those two
and that's not explicitly פר העלם דבר של ציבור בגופיה לא כתיב
par helam davar shel tzibbur begufei lo ksiv and it's not written
explicitly בהיקש אתיא. ba'hekesh atya. You only learn it because it's linked
to the פר par of the כהן משיח. kohen mashiach. From לפר?
l'par?
From well that's what it's going to link by the פר לפר.
par lapar. איצטריך לפר, Itztrach lapar, so normally it would just link
because you know it's juxtaposed and that's פשט pshat of the פסוק.
pasuk. But the somehow the understanding that this word לפר lapar is
extra allows us to say it's not just linked, since this word
לפר lapar is written here, it's like it's saying everything about that
cow is written, it's not just learn from, it's right here being
said in this פרשה parsha as well. And therefore, since it's explicit
in this פרשה, parsha, now we can export it. Okay, so ולא
להוי כמאן דכתיב ביה בגופיה, v'lo lehavi k'man de-ksiv bei b'gufei, it
should be like it's written in the thing itself, ולא להוי דבר
הלמד בהיקש חוזר ומלמד בהיקש, v'lo lehavi davar ha-lamed b'hekesh chozer u-melamed
b'hekesh, and not to be something that because you learned one link
you can't now export it in another link. Okay, that was all
very nice and complicated, and what we haven't even said yet was
how do we even know to apply or what's the basis of
applying this stuff to the שעירי עבודה זרה? se'irei avoda zara? Yesterday
we sort of talked about some way in which we applied it,
right? We had some היקש hekesh and then it went back or
whatever, but we have yet to say that explicitly. Okay, so we
want to get this stuff to apply to the goats of עבודה
זרה, avoda zara, that's our third category in addition to the יום
כיפור Yom Kippur stuff, which is also learned in a חטאת, chatas,
and so we got to get like stuff here so we can
make the link, but we haven't yet spelled out what that link
is, how we're actually going to do that. Okay, so that's actually
a little to what we transition to right now. Okay, so the
גמרא Gemara says like this: תניא
כוותיה דרב פפא, Tanya kevastei de-Rav Pappa, we taught like רב פפא,
Rav Pappa, meaning רב פפא's Rav Pappa basic idea that we learn
out things like, you know, let me just check רש"י Rashi what
exactly the תניא כוותיה Tanya kevastei is, oh yeah, I guess that
we link it to, that we link the two, we link the
two, you know, שעירי עבודה זרה se'irei avoda zara to this and
we learn the things out from the שעירי עבודה זרה. se'irei avoda
zara. So we taught like רב
פפא. Rav Pappa. Okay, דכתיב de-ksiv ועשה כאשר עשה, va'asah ka'asher asah,
מה תלמוד לומר לפר? mah talmud lomar lapar? What's לפר lapar doing?
לפי שנאמר le-fi she-ne'emar והם הביאו את קרבנם אשה לה', ve-hem heviu
et korbanam isheh l'Hashem, that's by this שעירי עבודה זרה, se'irei avoda
zara, וחטאתם ve-chatatam let's actually read that
פסוק. pasuk. וכי תשגו ולא תעשו את כל המצות האלה אשר דבר
ה' אל משה, ve-chi tishgu v'lo ta'asu et kol ha-mitzvot ha-eleh asher
diber Hashem el Moshe, so כל המצות kol ha-mitzvot is understood to
mean עבודה זרה, avoda zara, את כל אשר צוה ה' אליכם ביד
משה, et kol asher tziva Hashem aleichem b'yad Moshe, והיה אם מעיני
העדה נעשתה לשגגה, v'haya im me-einei ha-eidah ne'esta lishgaga, excuse me, that's
פר העלם דבר של ציבור, par helam davar shel tzibur,
wait a minute, no, it's פר העלם דבר של ציבור par helam
davar shel tzibur of עבודה זרה, avoda zara, okay, that's a separate
קרבן korban that the ציבור tzibur brings, and then you have the
individual doing
עבודה זרה. avoda zara. ונפש כי תחטא בשגגה והקריב עז בת שנתה
לחטאת, v'nefesh ki techeta bishgaga v'hikriv ez bat shenata l'chatas, okay, וכפר
הכהן על הנפש השוגגת בחטאה בשגגה, v'chiper ha-kohen al ha-nefesh ha-shogegat b'cheta'ah
bishgaga, והנפש אשר תעשה ve-ha-nefesh asher ta'aseh etc., one minute, hold on,
where am I? Okay,
oh so this actually is right, hold on.
What did you hear? They're citing כ"ה. kaf hey.
Yeah, yeah, yeah, so this is actually, so it's שעירי עבודה זרה,
se'irei avoda zara, but it's of, it's actually the case of שעירי
עבודה זרה, se'irei avoda zara, it is of פר העלם ציבור, par
helam tzibur, you know, of העלם בית דין, helam beit din, because
so it's when it's a subset or not a subset, but whatever,
a parallel case of פר העלם דבר של ציבור par helam davar
shel tzibur of הוריות. Horayos. So it is the, you bring actually
a פר par here for an עולה, olah, but the שעיר se'ir
is for the חטאת. chatas. Okay, so this is actually an inner
חטאת, chatas, it's עבודה זרה, avoda zara, but it's עבודה זרה avoda
zara when בית דין beit din פסק'נט paskened incorrectly. And the פסוק
pasuk says like this, is
it when בית דין beit din פסק'נט paskened or just a regular
person?
That's regular people sinning, right. Okay, and that's the next פרשה parsha
there which is also a שעיר se'ir but that's not the one
we're focusing on, okay. So here it says: ושעיר עזים אחד לחטאת,
u-se'ir izim echad l'chatas, וכפר הכהן על כל עדת בני ישראל ונסלח
להם כי שגגה היא והם הביאו את קרבנם אשה לה' וחטאתם לפני
ה' על שגגתם.
ve-chiper ha-kohen al kol adat bnei yisrael v'nislach lahem ki
shegaga hi v'hem heviu et korbanam isheh l'Hashem v'chatatam lifnei Hashem al
shegagatam.
And the
interesting
thing here is nowhere does it say that this is an inner
חטאת. chatas. So here's the real point: whereas here we know it's
an inner חטאת chatas and worrying about
details, is it מעכב me'akev by יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, do you
have
טבל אצבעו דם taval etzbao dam etc., here it just sounds like
it's a normal חטאת. chatas. But חז"ל Chazal probably assumed that since
it was a חטאת chatas of the ציבור, tzibur, because if you
think about this, right, the common denominator here is you don't have
an individual חטאת chatas that's an inner חטאת. chatas. The common denominator
here is that these are all חטאות chata'ot of the ציבור. tzibur.
Now you do have a חטאת chatas of a ציבור tzibur that's
an outer one, like the normal שעיר לחטאת se'ir l'chatas that's brought
on every, on every רגל, regel, okay, but certainly you do have
of a חטאת chatat *chattas*, all of these the common denominator, I
mean you could say the פר par *par* is the כהן גדול
Kohen Gadol. *kohen gadol*'s specific one, the פר par כהן משיח Kohen
Mashiach. *par kohen mashiach*, also a פר *par* of a כהן גדול
kohen gadol *kohen gadol*, but nevertheless פר *par* of a כהן גדול
*kohen gadol* sort of he sort of, it's a little more than
just any lay individual. Okay, so חז"ל Chazal *Chazal* understand, though here
it just says it's a חטאת chatat. *chattas*, but one of the
things that you have to appreciate is going on here, that can
get lost in all of these details, is that the פשט pshat
*pshat* here does not indicate at all that it's an inner חטאת
Chatat *chattas*. And that's part of what we're saying now. Okay, so
anyway, let's take a look. So רב פפא *Rav Pappa* just said
what are the reasons we need לפר lapar *lapar* here is in
order to apply some of these הלכות halachos *halachos* to this. But
now let's take a look at where how that's being done in
this ברייתא braisa *braisa*.
Okay, let's take a look. Where were we? תני כרב פפא: עשה
כאשר עשה, מה תלמוד לפר, lapar לפי שנאמר והם הביאו את קרבנם
אשה לה' חטאתם, אלו elu שעירי עבודת כוכבים, שגגתם, זה פר העלם
דבר של ציבור Par Helam Davar Shel Tzibbur, *Tani k'Rav Pappa: Asah
ka'asher asah, mah talmud lapar, lefi shene'emar v'hem heviu es korbanam ishe
l'Hashem
chattasam, elu seirei avodas kochavim,
shigagatam, zeh par helam davar shel tzibur*. Okay, so על חטאתם *al
chattasam*, this is what we're talking
about, this is your שעיר עבודה זרה se'ir avodah zarah *seir avodah
zarah*. תוספות Tosafot *Tosafos* says why is it plural שעירי עבודה זרה
se'irei avodah zarah. *seirei avodah zarah*? Anyway, על שגגתם *al shigagatam* is
your פר העלם דבר par helam davar *par helam davar* of ציבור
tzibur? *tzibur* there. And again, remember פר העלם דבר par helam davar
*par helam davar*, this is שעיר sa'ir. עבודה זרה *seir avodah zarah*
on העלם דבר *helam davar*. Let's not lose sight of that. That's
also part of what compels making the comparison. So this too links
this case of the שעיר *seir* of העלם דבר *helam davar* of
עבודה זרה *avodah zarah* to the פר *par* of העלם דבר *helam
davar*, and that lets us import everything from here to there. And
that's what we said before. We wanted to get the יותרת ושתי
הכליות Yoteret v'Shetei HaKelayot. *yoseres v'shtei haklayos* in פר העלם דבר par
helam davar *par helam davar* because we're going to be exporting all
this stuff.
I'm sorry, is this so self-referential? You just said... Yes, it is
self-referential. You just said חטאתם *chattasam* is שעיר עבודה זרה העלם דבר
*seir avodah zarah helam davar*, which one are we talking about here?
Yes, this חטאתם *chattasam* that we're talking about here is compared to
the פר העלם דבר Par Helam Davar. *par helam davar* that we're
talking about over there. They're both העלם דבר *helam davar*. This is
etc. etc. So therefore they're being linked, and that by this פסוק
pasuk *pasuk* for what?
For what purpose? To...
because we don't know anything about this. We don't know that it's
an inner חטאת Chatat *chattas*, we don't know what's מעכב me'akev. *me'akev*,
we know nothing about how to do this חטאת Chatat. *chattas*. So
this link allows us to export all of that stuff. And the
whole לפר lapar *lapar* here is to include in that export, to
include the issue of the יותרת ושתי הכליות Yoteret v'Shetei HaKelayot, *yoseres
v'shtei haklayos*. Okay, הרי לך חטאתם, שגגתם, אמרה תורה חטאתם הרי היא
לך כשגגתם *Harei lecha chattasam, shigagatam, amrah Torah chattasam harei hi lacha
k'shigagatam*. Okay, so this חטאת Chatat *chattas*, this חטאת chatas *chattas* is
like this שגגתם *shigagatam* is like all the stuff we did over
there by the פר העלם דבר של ציבור Tzibbur *par helam davar
shel tzibur*. שגגתם היכן למדתה? *Shigagatam heichan lamadeta?* But one minute. How
do we know that this שגגתם *shigagatam*, how do we know this
stuff here like the הזיית דם וטבילה *hazayas hadam v'hatvilah*, the יותרת
ושתי הכליות Yoteret Shetei HaKelayot, *yoseres v'shtei haklayos*, how do you know
it all applies over here? It's a היקש hekesh, *hekesh*. So now
we got a problem. You can't export all of it. וכי דבר
הלמד בהיקש חוזר ומלמד בהיקש? davar ha-lamed b'hekesh hozer u-melamed b'hekesh. *V'chi
davar halamad b'hekesh chozer u'melamed b'hekesh?* No, because that's one of the
principles we have by קדשים *kodshim* that you can't export something if
you learned it from somewhere else. תלמוד לומר לפר, lapar זה פר
העלם דבר של ציבור, Tzibbur. לפר, lapar, זה פר כהן המשיח par
kohen hamashiach *Talmud lomar lapar, zeh par helam davar shel tzibur, lapar,
zeh par kohen hamashiach*. Okay, so that's what I said to you,
where this פסוק pasuk *pasuk* is going to allow us to import
everything from here, to link this שעיר עבודה זרה *seir avodah zarah*
of העלם דבר *helam davar* of ציבור tzibur *tzibur* to the פר
העלם דבר *par helam davar*. This says almost nothing in this case.
This is going to allow us to import all this stuff. Before
we import this, we want to get everything into the package. So
we're going to use the לפר lapar *lapar* to sort of package
it all together.
Okay, now let's get back. אמר מר: חטאתם אלו שעירי עבודת כוכבים
*Amar mar: Chattasam elu seirei avodas kochavim*.
תיפוק ליה מקרא קמא *teipok lei mikra kama*, דאמר מר: החטאת, hachatat
ריבה שעירי עבודת כוכבים *d'amar mar: hachattas, ribah seirei avodas kochavim*. So
now we've got a... מקרא קמא *mikra kama* is not over here.
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says wait a minute, why do we need this
to be the vehicle to import all this stuff? Over here it
says... right, remember,
we used עשה כאשר עשה *asah ka'asher asah*
seven plus four etc., לפר lapar, *lapar* is is this category of
יום כיפור Yom Kippur *Yom Kippur*, but then we said החטאת hachatat
*hachattas* gives us the third category of שעירי עבודת כוכבים *seirei avodas
kochavim*. So basically now we can appreciate by the way, now we
can
appreciate what was going on here, because basically here you have in
high detail what you do with an inner חטאת chatas *chattas* by
the פר כהן משיח *par kohen mashiach* and the פר העלם דבר
של ציבור tzibur *par helam davar shel tzibur*. Okay, here by פר
יום הכיפורים *par Yom Hakippurim* you have a lot of detail and
actually some stuff is more, but you don't have all of the
detail. And here you have nothing. And חז"ל *Chazal* basically understood, look,
it's a חטאת chatat. *chattas* of the ציבור *tzibur*, it's just like
a פר העלם דבר *par helam davar*, it's just about עבודה זרה
*avodah zarah* and in many ways it's worse, so obviously it's assumed
this stuff has to apply over here. How are we going to
do it? So it did it with these two words. Okay, ועשה
כאשר עשה v'asar ka-asher asa כן יעשה *v'asah ka'asher asah kein ya'aseh*
was... to tell me it's מעכב me'akev. and these two words לפר
lapar exports it to יום כיפור Yom Kippur and חטאת chatat, exports
it to the שעיר עבודה זרה of the שעירי עבודה זרה. se'irei
avodah zarah Okay, so that's now we can step back and appreciate,
you know, what was being done big picture. Now the question is
what is making this the link from פר העלם דבר to the
שעירי עבודה זרה se'irei avodah zarah? of the ציבור? Is it this
word החטאת here by פר העלם דבר or is it חטאתם אשר
שגו שם chatatam asher shagu sham here by שעירי עבודה זרה? se'irei
avodah zarah. That's the only question right now. So let's take a
look.
So you don't need to actually have like גזירה שוה, gezeirah shavah,
you just need to just it's sort of like a ריבוי, ribui,
is that what we're saying? It's not actually linked.
How can they link the same word? Right, right, it's not linked
by the same word. It's linked, yeah, it's somehow the ריבוי, ribui,
the extra word is telling you. Well, part of the point though
is you have to understand is that and this happens in some
other places too, like we have it by the שבעת ימי המילואים
shivat yemei hamiluim where it says וכאשר עשה ביום הזה צוה ה'
לעשות לכפר עליכם vika'asher asa bayom hazeh tziva Hashem la'asot lachaper aleichem
right by the seven days of preparation, so it's צוה ה' לעשות
tziva Hashem la'asot אלו יום כיפור Yom Kippur where we have the
seven days of preparation for יום כיפור Yom Kippur or לעשות la'asot
I think or means like מעשה פרה, ma'aseh parah, seven days to
prepare for פרה אדומה, parah adumah, לכפר עליכם lachaper aleichem אלו מעשה
אילו יום כיפור. elu ma'aseh eilu Yom Kippur. So if a פסוק
pasuk is explicitly saying do here, do this in case X, now
in both of the what's similar to the example I've just given
you in this, in both of them the פשט pshat, is do
this here, but because it says it in a verbose way we
say no, what it's actually saying is do this also in these
other related cases. So I don't even know if this falls into
one of the classic י"ג מדות yod gimmel middot because what we're
really saying is look, it's not a ריבוי, ribui, it's not a
היקש, hekesh, it's not a גזירה שוה, gezeirah shavah, it's saying do
this to other things, do what we're doing here to the פר
and to the חטאת. chatat Now of course for us that's not
פשט, pshat okay, but it's not like an extra word, an extra
letter, a גזירה שוה, gezeirah shavah, we're saying the פסוק pasuk is
saying do this in these cases. We're telling you what these cases
means is יום כיפור Yom Kippur, and, you know, שעירי עבודה זרה.
Se'irei Avodah Zarah Alright, so anyway, but a so the good question,
like what exactly is the technical, you know, hermeneutic principle. Anyway, now
the question is is it the לפר Lapor. here that's exporting it
or is it the חטאתם אשר שגו שם? chatatam asher shagu sham?
Okay, this is more of a היקש, this is not saying do
this like you did it, this is just saying these two are
similar. Okay, so it says like this, אמר מר חטאתם אלו שעירי
עבודת כוכבים לתפוק ליה מקרא קמא דאמר מר החטאת ריבה בשעירי עבודת
כוכבים אמר רב פפא איצטריך סלקא דעתך אמינא הני מילי הזאות דכתיבי
בגופיה. amar mar chatatam eilu se'irei avodat kochavim letipok lei mikra kama
de'amar mar hachatat riba bise'irei avodat kochavim amar Rav Papa itztareich salka
deitach amina hanei mili haza'ot dechtivei beguphaih. Ah,
this is sort of things that we sort of have said before,
okay. That maybe and this sort of gets back to our other
point. This idea that you apply all of this, maybe that's the
stuff that's explicit here. What's explicit here? What's explicit here is all
of the blood work. Okay, what's not explicit here is the stuff
that we learn out from up there. What's not explicit here is
the, you know, טבל את דמו taval et damo and the והיותרת
ושתי הכליות. vehayoteret ushtei hakelayot. So that's why, right, the לפר Lapor
here is not, that's so, okay, so אבל יותרת ושתי כליות דלא
כתיבי
בגופיה אימא לא קמשמע לן aval yoteret ushtei kelayot dela keitvei beguphaih
eima lo kamashma lan
that that actually is going to be learned. So now it's not
exactly clear whether we do it from the לפר Lapor point, but
anyway, if it were just the החטאת here it would have just
applied the blood stuff. The extra פסוק pasuk. which fully links them
is sort of saying apply it also to the stuff that's not
explicit here but that you learned out, not explicit in פר העלם
דבר but that you learned from פר כהן המשיח which here the
גמרא Gemara is saying is היותרת ושתי הכליות hayoteret ushtei hakelayot but
based on yesterday we could have also said it's טבל את דמו.
taval et damo. Now the only thing is the difference though of
what we said a minute ago, yeah, so what it's saying is
you need to sort of learn out the whole package. The difference
here is that here it's saying the way we're doing it is
because of this חטאתם אשר שגו שם chatatam asher shagu sham whereas
a minute ago we said the way we're doing it was through
the word of לפר, Lapor that the word of לפר Lapor packaged
it all together. Okay, but the difference might be that this was
a רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael דרשה. drasha. Okay, either what it's showing
is we need to package this stuff down here. For רבי ישמעאל
Rabbi Yishmael we do it maybe with the word לפר, Lapor right,
remember cause he didn't need this for יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, so
לפר Lapor packages this all together, and for the non-רבי ישמעאל Rabbi
Yishmael we do it from this extra דרשה drasha of חטאתם אשר
שגו שם. chatatam asher shagu sham. Okay, but that's the basic idea.
We package it all together and then we export
it.
The רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael we got this from, is that the
same רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael from the thirteen? Yeah, okay, cause I'm
trying to figure, I'm trying to fit that into
the, go, go for it. Okay, אמר ליה רב הונא בריה דרב
נתן לרב פפא, amar lei Rav Huna breih deRav Natan leRav Papa,
והתנא פר יום הכפורים לכל מה שאמור בענין קאמר, vehatana par Yom
Hakippurim lechol mah she'amur be'inyan ka'amar, but one minute, okay,
the, but the תנא tanna says now I gotta, there's a whole
debate of רש"י Rashi תוספות Tosafot how to read this. So let
me just remind myself, check how תוספות Tosafot is reading this.
Okay,
so the way he reads it is the following. When we said,
this is so technical, let's just get through this, okay, as if
it weren't technical until now. But here's his problem. You said you
needed this extra חטאת היא שגגתם Chatat Hi Sh'gatan in order to
import the יותרת ושתי הכליות. He says but one minute, when we
learned out this stuff to יום כיפור, Yom Kippur. we did it
from the word of לפר. Right? Remember that's how we learned this
out for יום כיפור. Yom Kippur Nobody ever told us we needed
something extra to export this stuff to יום כיפור Yom Kippur to
include like טבל את ובדם Taval Et v'Badam or the יותרת ושתי
הכליות, right? That wasn't written in this thing itself. But somehow לפר
was enough to say just export everything. Okay, right? Because when we
did יום כיפור Yom Kippur, we didn't need some extra דרשה drasha
for this stuff. So if, for this is how תוספות Tosafos reads
so if לפר was enough to export everything, חטאת chatat should be
enough to export everything. And why do you need an additional דרשה
drasha over here to, to get all this extra stuff?
Okay, I mean why do you need that other פסוק pasuk.
חטאת היא שגגתם? Chatat Hi Sh'gatan? Right. So if לפר could export
everything to יום כיפור, Yom Kippur even the stuff that's not explicit
here, then חטאת chatat should be able to export everything to שעירי
עבודה זרה Se'irei Avodah Zarah. even without an extra פסוק. pasuk Okay,
אמר ליה Amar lei רב הונא בריה דרב נתן Rav Huna brei
de-Rav Natan לרב פפא le-Rav Pappa ותנא פוטר ביום הכיפורים לכל מה
שאמר בעניין קמא? Vatana potair b'Yom HaKippurim le-chol mah she-amar be-inyan kama?
But the תנא Tanna said that the לפר tells you everything applies
to the case of יום כיפור Yom Kippur and you didn't need
an extra פסוק. So how come you're explaining here that you needed
a חטאת היא שגגתם Chatat Hi Sh'gatan to package it all together?
Just learn it all from the extra word חטאת. chatat So the
גמרא Gemara. says, תנאי היא. Tannai hi. You're right, it's a debate
of תנאים Tannaim whether you need an extra word or פסוק or
whatever to package it all together. תנא דבי רבי מרבי הכי Tana
de-bei Rabbi marbi hachi תנא דבי רבי ישמעאל לא מרבי הכי. Tana
de-bei Rabbi Yishmael lo marbi hachi. The תנא דבי רבי ישמעאל, Tana
de-bei Rabbi Yishmael, this is sort of what I was saying before,
that needed the לפר to like pull all the stuff down and
so on, he's the one that needed this extra stuff to be
packaged together and to be exported. The earlier תנא Tanna which was
a תנא דבי רבי Tana de-bei Rabbi which said, which said לכל
מה שאמר בעניין le-chol mah she-amar be-inyan here, he doesn't need an
extra thing to package it all together.
What does he do with the extra thing then?
I don't know. I'm just getting through this at this stage. Okay,
anyway, תנא דבי רבי ישמעאל לא מרבי הכי. Tana de-bei Rabbi Yishmael
lo marbi hachi. תנא דבי רבי ישמעאל מפני מה נאמרו שתי כליות
Tana de-bei Rabbi Yishmael mipnei mah ne'emru shetei kelayot so בפר כהן
משיח b'Par Kohen Mashiach ולא נאמרו... v'lo ne'emru... Okay, okay fine, period.
We are now done. Okay, take a breath. The basic point is,
the upshot of all of this is, the extra things that are
here, יותרת ושתי הכליות, טבל את ובדם Taval Et v'Badam whatever, they're
linked, they apply to פר העלם דבר. ועשה כאשר עשה says the
seven and the four are
מעכב. me'akev. וכפר v'chipper says the שריים shirayim and the סמיכה semichah
are not מעכב. me'akev, לפר applies all of this to יום כיפור
Yom Kippur and חטאת Chatas. applies all of this to שעירי עבודה
זרה. se'irei avoda zara That is the basic point. Okay, and some
of the extra words you needed maybe to package some of the
stuff together because דבר הלמד בהיקש חוזר ומלמד בהיקש. The one thing
by the way I should say that is still debated, that we
didn't discuss, is the possibility that on יום כיפור Yom Kippur. the
שריים shirayim is מעכב. me'akev, Okay, so here the שריים shirayim is
not מעכב, me'akeiv actually there's some discussion about that. There's actually some
discussion about the פנימיות חטאות inner chatatot as well, some שיטות shitot
that the שפיכת שריים. shefichat shirayim. So although here we're saying שריים
shirayim is not מעכב, me'akeiv, you should just be aware that that's
to some degree there is some debate around that. Okay, now we
can take a breath. Now it gets a little bit, we get
a sort of a little bonus אגדתא Aggadeta for having, you know,
sort of soldiered through that. Okay, or aggadic-ish. Okay, תנא דבי רבי
ישמעאל מפני מה נאמרו יותרת ושתי כליות בפר כהן משיח ולא נאמרו
בפר העלם דבר של ציבור Tana de-bei Rabbi Yishmael mipnei mah ne'emru
yoteret v'shetei kelayot b'Par Kohen Mashiach v'lo ne'emru b'Par Helam Davar Shel
Tzibbur? Why if it's going to repeat everything in the פר העלם
דבר של ציבור, why is the one thing that didn't get repeated
this issue about the, you know, about the אימורים, emurim, the specifics
about the אימורים, emurim, the lobe of the liver and the two
kidneys? משל למלך בשר ודם שזעם על אוהבו ומיעט בסרחונו מפני חיבתו.
Mashal le-melech basar va-dam she-zaam al ohavo v'mi'et b'sirchono mipnei hibato. It's
like when a king, a human king gets angry on, on a
אוהבו ohavo on somebody he loves, so he's not going to go
on and on and on in heavy detail because he wants to
sort of make more, you know, when he's sort of listing the
punishment or whatever it is because he wants to, you know, save
him from the disgrace to that degree. So basically, it's interesting, who's
the אוהבו ohavo here? Right, you would have thought that the אוהבו
ohavo maybe is the כהן משיח. That's an interesting statement. No, this
is the this is the ציבור or if you want the בית
דין Beit Din that represents the ציבור. Okay, so not the כהן
גדול. So anyway, so the short is, so because this is like
this represents all of כלל ישראל, Klal Yisrael, we're going to not
say the full detail. It's still a pretty long פרשה parsha here.
Okay, but we're not going to say every lit- little last detail.
Okay,
now,
ותנא דבי רבי ישמעאל, Ve'tanna de'bei Rabbi Yishmael, another teaching דבי רבי
ישמעאל, de'bei Rabbi Yishmael, מפני מה נאמר פרוכת הקודש בפר כהן המשיח
mipnei ma ne'emar paroches hakodesh be'par kohen hamashiach ולא בפר העלם דבר
של ציבור? ve'lo be'par he'elam davar shel tzibur? When it says you
sprinkle it on the פרוכת, paroches, here it says מפני פרוכת הקודש
mipnei paroches hakodesh and this just says פרוכת. paroches. It doesn't have
the word קודש. kodesh. Okay, so משל למלך בשר ודם mashal le'melech
basar vadam שסרחה עליו מדינה, she'sarcha alav medina, so a country rebelled
against him. אם מיעוטה סרחה, im mi'uta sarcha, if only a minority
of that country rebelled against him, obviously they're drawing on Roman history,
you know, where Rome had to deal with putting down rebellions of
its various provinces and so on, not just Judea. Anyway, so if
only the minority of it rebelled, פמליא שלו מתקיימת. pamalya shelo miskayemes.
His פמליא, pamalya, his like retinue, you know, is still established. It
doesn't like undermine his general supporters that he has in, you know.
But אם רובה סרחה, im ruba sarcha, but if the majority of
the country is rebelling against him, then אין פמליא שלו מתקיימת. ein
pamalya shelo miskayemes. He loses, you know, his like inner circle of
supporters. And פמליא, pamalya, I mean obviously the word family, it's a
word that, you know, the חז"ל use to sort of speak about
פמליא של מעלה, pamalya shel ma'ala, the divine heavenly retinue, like, you
know, so God's, you know, holy like all the angels or whatever
it is, you know, that sort of that's there as part of
God's
retinue. Anyway, so,
the point is is that here, okay, the כהן גדול sinned, but
it's still the holy פרוכת. paroches. When the ציבור sins, it's as
if the holiness of the פרוכת paroches has gone away. It's as
if it even undermines, it's not just their sin, it somehow undermines,
you know, God's presence and God's sanctity in this world because of
that and there's even a sense that that has lost its holiness.
So even in the inner sanctum of God's place, if you would,
in God's palace, right, some of the קדושה kedusha has gone away
because the ציבור has sinned.
Okay,
so we are now moving on. Okay, לפיכך, lefichach, alright, I'm going
to erase all of this just to prove that we are totally
done with this. All of that was to tell you, was started
with the idea that at the פנימיות חטאות penimiyos chataos you need
the four applications of blood and they're all מעכב me'akeiv. plus the
seven and that applies to all of these other פנימיות חטאות penimiyos
chataos even the שעירי עבודה זרה that are themselves not explicit that
they're a חטאת פנימית. chatas penimis. And now what we are doing
is getting to the to one of the הלכות about the four
inner about the four applications. Since they're all מעכב, me'akev and that
is of course cause everything, the נפקא מינה nafka mina is for
פיגול. pigul. Okay, so once we get through the fact that you
need to do all four and if not the קרבן korban isn't
good, the משנה mishna goes on to say what's the implication is
for פיגול. pigul. And the implication for פיגול pigul is that if
you did one of them with a פיגול pigul thought and the
others with non-פיגול pigul thought, okay, then it's still כשר kosher because
you did not have a פיגול pigul thought through the entire act.
The entire act constitutes all four applications, actually four plus seven. Okay,
and this is the principle and I love this phrase because it's
just so terse and this is like one of the most a
combination of some of the most obscure things that we're learning, right,
exactly, אין מפגלין
בחצי
מתיר. ein mefaglin be'chatzi matir. Okay, which means you cannot create פיגול
pigul if you're doing it only on something that's a partial part
of that stage. Okay, so you do פיגול pigul by שחיטה, shechita,
הולכה, holacha, קבלה, kabala, and זריקה. zerika. So what if you only
did it during half of that stage? By שחיטה shechita you can
have half because you can שחט, shacht, you know, one of the
what do you call it, you know, the trachea not the esophagus.
You couldn't say by הולכה holacha you have half because you could
walk half the distance. But that's not considered half because those are
not discrete stages, discrete pieces, okay, that's just quantitative, okay, or whatever,
but it's just not discrete. But the other case is by the
application of the four of the four corners of the blood. Normally
by the other things one application is a מעכב. So beyond that,
since it's not necessary, you can create פיגול. pigul. But here if
you have to do all four corners of the inner חטאת and
seven, then, you know, if you're if your פיגול pigul was only
part of that, you don't create פיגול. pigul. Okay, so that's what
the משנה mishna says. So let's take a look at the גמרא.
Gemara
תנן התם, tnan hatam, we taught over there, over in מנחות. Menachos.
פיגל בקומץ ולא בלבונה. pigel be'komets ve'lo bi'levona. Here's another case of
a חצי מתיר. chatzi matir. What's offered up by the מנחה? mincha?
The handbreadth plus the frankincense. So if you had a פיגול pigul
thought by the קומץ kometz and not the לבונה, levona, בלבונה ולא
בקומץ, bi'levona ve'lo be'komets, or the reverse, רבי מאיר אומר פיגול וחייבין
עליו כרת. Rabbi Meir omer pigul ve'chayavin alav kares. רבי מאיר Rabbi
Meir says it's פיגול, pigul, presumably, we're going to discuss this in
a minute, רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir holds מפגלין בחצי מתיר. mefaglin be'chatzi
matir. וחכמים
אומרים אין בו כרת, ve'chachamim omrim ein bo kares, no, there's no
כרת kares עד שיפגל בכל המתיר. ad she'yefagel be'chol hamatir. There's the
phrase, you have to have פיגול pigul by all of the stages
of this all of the parts of this one stage. Now by
the way as תוספות Tosafot points out, the פשט pshat of those
is that for the חכמים Chachamim it is פסול, pasul, it's just
not פיגול. pigul. Wow. But תוספות *Tosafos* points to another גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* that implies that it's actually not פסול pasul. *pasul* if you
just do a חצי מתיר matir, *chatzi matir*. תוספות *Tosafos* actually says
that if it's פסול pasul *pasul*, it's only פסול pasul *pasul* rabbinically.
So that's a side point. For the rabbis, if you had פיגול
piggul. *pigul* for the trachea and not the esophagus, for the קומץ
*chomitz* and not the לבונה *levonah*, for one of the four inner
corners and not the others, it's pas—for רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir *Rebbe
Meir* it's פיגול piggul *pigul*, for the חכמים *Chachamim* it's פסול pasul
*pasul*, but for תוספות *Tosafos* it's only פסול pasul מדרבנן mi-derabbanan, *pasul
mi-d'rabbanan*, so just an interesting parenthetical point. Yeah.
אמר רבי שמעון בן לקיש *Amar Rebbe Shimon ben Lakish*—because again it's
sort of like a חצי מתיר *chatzi matir*, is that it?
It is a חצי מתיר *chatzi matir*.
What do you mean? No, meaning just like trachea and the esophagus.
Yeah, yeah, this is exactly the חצי מתיר *chatzi matir*. The question
is what happens when you are, if פיגול piggul. *pigul* doesn't get
created by חצי מתיר *chatzi matir*, does anything happen? Does it invalidate
the קרבן korban *korban*? Okay, so the implication here is yes, but
תוספות *Tosafos* says that's only rabbinic.
So would we also have to think חוץ לזמנו *chutz l'zmano* on
both of them
or—Yes, yes,
I mean חוץ למקומו chutz limkomo. *chutz limkomo* on both of them,
or it would be פסול pasul דאורייתא *pasul d'Oraisa*.
Yeah. אמר רבי שמעון בן לקיש *Amar Rebbe Shimon ben Lakish*—Who is
תוספות *Tosafos*—לא תימא טעמיה דרבי מאיר דקסבר מפגלין בחצי מתיר mefaglin bechatzi
matir, *Lo teima ta'amei d'Rebbe Meir d'kasavar mifaglin b'chatzi matir*, which is
of course the simplest thing to say about רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir
*Rebbe Meir*. Don't think that's his principle, that if you do it
by חצי מתיר *chatzi matir*. אלא הכא במאי עסקינן *Ela hacha b'mai
askinan*, רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir *Rebbe Meir* when he says it's פיגול
piggul *pigul*, he really agrees that you need to be מפגל בכל
המתיר mefagel bechol hamatir *mifagel b'chol ha-matir*. And he's only talking about
a specific case where it works to do it only at one
of the stages. כגון kegon שנתן את הקומץ במחשבה והלבונה בשתיקה *K'gon
shenasan es ha-kometz b'machshava v'ha-levona b'shtika*. That you did the first stage,
רש"י Rashi *Rashi* says it doesn't really matter whether it's the קומץ
*kometz* or the לבונה *levonah*, but the first thing you did, you
did it with a פיגול piggul *pigul* thought, and the next thing
you did with a שתיקה shtika *shtika*, silence, with no פיגול piggul.
*pigul* thought. And it's not because it works sufficiently to do it
by חצי מתיר *chatzi matir*, but it's that וקסבר כל העושה על
דעת ראשונה הוא עושה kol ha'oseh al da'as rishona hu oseh. *v'kasavar
kol ha-oseh al da'as rishona hu oseh*. If you start a process
with that thought, that thought defines the rest of the process unless
you actively redefine. So for רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir. *Rebbe Meir* he
says if you had the thought during the second stage, during the
application of, you know, the לבונה *levonah* if it came after the
קומץ *kometz*, if you had it during corners number two or number
three or number four, but corner number one was not a פיגול
piggul *pigul* thought, you're safe. You did not have the thought for
all four. רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir *Rebbe Meir* needs the פיגול piggul
*pigul* thought for all of the components, but he just says if
it's your first thought, it defines the rest unless you actively redefine.
Now before we continue to analyze that, little digression here, important point
that רש"י *Rashi* makes, it's come up in the past, what the
word the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* uses to frame that you're not having
a פיגול piggul *pigul* thought is שתיקה shtika. *shtika*, silence, okay, which
suggests that the פיגול piggul *pigul* thought is an articulated one, okay.
So it doesn't say בלי מחשבת פיגול machshevet pigul. *beli machshavas pigul*.
Now maybe it's a shorthand, but if you look at רש"י *Rashi*,
this is a long-standing discussion that רש"י *Rashi* and תוספות *Tosafos* have
going back way back to the first משנה mishna *Mishnah* about a
thought of שלא לשמו shelo lishmo. *shelo lishmo*. Does the thinking that
invalidates קרבנות *korbanos*, does it have to be articulated or not? So
if you just take a one minute to read this in רש"י
*Rashi* where רש"י *Rashi* says, where's רש"י *Rashi*?
Okay, במחשבה
*b'machshava*. So רש"י *Rashi* says, וכל מחשבה machshava?
*v'chol machshava*. The first one in the רש"י *Rashi* is מחשבה machshavah.
*machshava*, it is about, it's
almost—you see where it says the line ends בחצי מתיר *b'chatzi matir*
in the גמרא Gemara. *Gemara* that we just
read? If you go right across from that in the רש"י *Rashi*
you see רש"י *Rashi* says, he says מחשבה machshavah. דקדשים מוציא בפיו
*machshava d'kodshim motzi b'pihu*.
When we talk about thought during קרבן *korban*, we mean articulated thought,
okay. אבל aval ושונה בשתיקה *Aval v'shoneh b'shtika* etc. דאין כאן אלא
מחשבת חצי מתיר *d'ein kan ela machshavas chatzi matir*. So I just
want you to see those four words in רש"י *Rashi*, מחשבה machshavah.
דקדשים מוציא בפיו *machshava d'kodshim motzi b'pihu*, those five words, okay. Which
he picks up on the fact that the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says
שתיקה shtika, *shtika*. It's another, it's a similar point that תוספות *Tosafos*
makes. Never said explicitly in the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*. It's only an
unarticulated thought in the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* anyway, but רש"י *Rashi* and
תוספות *Tosafos* both say, you know, based on this and other considerations
that מחשבה *machshava* means articulated. Anyway, back to the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*.
So, either the rabbis could—David? Yeah, could you say that this is
like a חזקה *chazaka* with like טומאה *tumah* and טהרה *tahara*, like
a נדה *Niddah*? You know,
I've been reading like משנה mishna נדה *Mishnah Niddah* right now. So
this idea of like, you know, if she
was—Yeah, you need something to actively change the status. It's similar. It's
a little different. חזקה *chazaka* is like a status and a status
creates a threshold of either proof or whatever that you need, you
know, presumptions that it remains until you change it. So you're right.
This sort of, it's similar. I don't know if I would have
defined it as a חזקה *chazaka*, I more would have sort of
said that, you know, the act is defined by its beginning unless
it's actively redefined. So but it is similar that once something gets
a certain type of an identity, it creates a higher thresh—like that
sticks with it and it requires some more active thing to change
that identity. So there is definitely some parallel there. Yeah.
But according to רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir *Rebbe Meir* everyone would agree,
right, if even if you hold
חצי *chatzi*— No if you hold מפלגין בחצי maflagin b'chatzi. it could
be any one. Oh okay. So what we're saying is רבי מאיר
Rabbi Meir doesn't hold מפלגין בחצי. He needs that you have to
have פיגול בכל המתיר. piggul b'chol hamatir. But if you do it
at the beginning it's defined as you have it for the whole
thing.
Which means if you didn't if you just did if
you did it in the middle it doesn't make פיגול. piggul That's
exactly his point. Okay now the גמרא Gemara says ממאי mi-mai what
makes you say that that for רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir it's only
because that was your first מחשבה? מדתני mi-de-tani
לפיכך אם נתן כולם כתיקנן ואחת שלא כתיקנן פסול ואין בו כרת.
lefikach im natan kulam ke-tiknan ve-achas she-lo ke-tiknan pasul ve-ein bo kares.
Okay because our משנה mishna says our משנה mishna is not clear
whether it holds like רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir or not. Our משנה
mishna says since you have these four applications of blood on the
inner חטאת that are מעכב therefore if you did one if you
did
all of them properly and one of them improperly okay it is
not פיגול piggul but it is
פסול. pasul Okay so
he's going to read that משנה mishna as the order matters. So
the משנה mishna said if you did all of them meaning the
way he's reading the משנה mishna the first three properly and the
last one improperly then it is פסול pasul but not פיגול. piggul.
So he says one minute הא אחת שלא כתיקנה ha-achas she-lo ke-tikna
maybe that suggests that if the order were reversed if the first
one were פיגול piggul הא אחת שלא כתיקנה וכולן כתיקנן ha-achas she-lo
ke-tikna ve-kulan ke-tiknan and the rest were proper without any thought פיגול
piggul. it would be פיגול. piggul So מני mani who is this
going like? אילימא רבנן eileima rabbanan if it's the רבנן rabbanan הא
אמרי רבנן אין מפלגין בחצי המתיר ha amri rabbanan ein maflagin b'chatzi
hamatir for the רבנן rabbanan it doesn't matter if it's a פיגול
piggul thought for only one of them then it doesn't make it.
So the משנה mishna should have been clearer that for the רבנן
rabbanan that order doesn't matter. If it were going like the רבנן
rabbanan and it should have said no matter which one you have
a פיגול piggul thought it's not פיגול piggul until you have a
thought for all four of them okay or something like that. The
משנה mishna the way his way of reading the משנה mishna I'm
not so convinced that that's necessarily indicated in the משנה mishna but
his way of reading it the משנה mishna says that the order
matters. So for the רבנן rabbanan the order doesn't matter it's never
פיגול piggul. no matter when you have that thought unless it's for
all four. Okay so הא מני? ha mani? אימא רבי מאיר eima
Rabbi Meir it's רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir So רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir
would say if you have the פיגול piggul thought so the way
he's reading it is if the פיגול piggul thought came at the
end it's not פיגול. piggul If the פיגול piggul thought came at
the beginning it is פיגול. piggul Who is that? Okay can't be
the רבנן rabbanan the רבנן rabbanan say you need פיגול piggul at
all four stages. So it must be רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir and
it must be that רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir only says this הלכה
halacha when the פיגול piggul thought comes at the beginning not when
it comes in the middle or the end. ואי טעמא דרבי מאיר
משום דמפלגין בחצי המתיר ve-ei taama de-Rabbi Meir mishum de-maflagin b'chatzi hamatir
but if רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir, was of the opinion of מפלגין
בחצי המתיר maflagin b'chatzi hamatir הוא אפילו כי דקתני נמי hu afilu
ki dekatané nami so then even if the פיגול piggul thought came
at the end anyway the פיגול piggul. thought came it would have
made
פיגול. piggul לאו משום דקסבר lav mishum de-kasavar it must be that
if this read of the משנה mishna is correct that at the
beginning פיגול piggul a פיגול piggul. thought makes it פיגול piggul at
the end it makes it פסול pasul but not פיגול pigul. okay
if that's true it must be that רבי מאיר's Rabbi Meir. position
is not מפלגין בחצי המתיר maflagin b'chatzi hamatir but that a פיגול
pigul. thought at the beginning defines the whole process. לאו משום דקסבר
כל העושה על דעת ראשונה הוא עושה lav mishum de-kasavar kol ha-oseh
al daat rishonah hu oseh and that must be רבי מאיר's Rabbi
Meir, position. So that's how he gets it by a משנה mishna
that doesn't even say who it's going like but he's going to
but based on his way of reading it the way of reading
that order matters he's going to decide the משנה mishna is רבי
מאיר Rabbi Meir and it's telling you even for רבי מאיר Rabbi
Meir it's only when the פיגול pigul comes first. Okay let's see
what the גמרא Gemara says. The גמרא Gemara is going to push
back on this. Okay now it's not going to push back the
reason I would I would have just said I don't think the
משנה mishna is implying that order matters. The משנה Mishnah. is saying
if you do it okay for three and not okay for one
it's a problem okay it's not telling you it's saying anything about
order. That's not going to be the גמרא. Gemara The גמרא Gemara
is going to buy into his assumption to read the משנה Mishnah
that order matters but let's see how the גמרא Gemara is going
to read it push
back. Okay אמר רב שמואל בר יצחק amar Rav Shmuel bar Yitzchak
לעולם רבנן היא le-olam rabbanan hi it's the רבנן. rabbanan. ומאי כתיקנן?
ve-mai ke-tiknan? כתיקנן לפיגול. ke-tiknan le-piggul. It's just shows you the irony
right the same way that by פיגול pigul we say it has
to be מרצה mirtzeh everything else has to be done properly or
whatever so we're saying the word כתיקנן ke-tiknan doesn't mean that you
did it the way a קרבן is supposed to be it means
you did it satisfying all the requirements of פיגול pigul if you
wanted to make it into פיגול. pigul, So כתיקנן ke-tiknan means you
did it with a פיגול pigul, thought. Okay so it says it's
very bizarre. Okay so it says so it reads like this it
says נתן כולם כתיקנן ואחת שלא כתיקנן פסול ולא פיגול.
natan kulam ke-tiknan ve-achas she-lo ke-tiknan pasul
ve-lo piggul.
Now
this is referring to what the חטאת הפנימית?
Chatas ha-Penimis? This is חטאת הפנימיות Chatas ha-Penimiyos okay פסול ולא פיגול.
pasul ve-lo piggul.
Now the way the way he is reading it is okay the
first three were שתיקה shtika. and then the last one is פיגול
pigul or whatever so it's not it's פסול pasul. and no פיגול.
pigul. But he says if it were the reverse but this is
the way he reads it if it were number one was פיגול
pigul and the next three were two through four were שתיקה. shtika,
Then he would say that would be פיגול. pigul Okay, that was
his way of reading it. So that has to be רבי מאיר
Rabbi Meir and if it's רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir order matters and
that is his read of רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir Okay, that's his
way of reading it. The גמרא Gemara is saying no, let's read
it the following way. נתנן כולן כתיקנן, Nasan kulan kitiknan,
כתיקנן kitiknan means מחשבת פיגול. pigul The type of doing it the
right way if you wanted to make it פיגול. pigul. Okay? So
if you had one through three with a פיגול pigul thought, okay,
and then you had number four with a שתיקה, shtika. okay, then
it's going to be פסול pasul why because it's the Rabbis of
אין מפגלין בחצי מתיר ein mefaglin b'chatzi matir and you don't have
all four of them, okay, with that type of a thought. Okay?
So let's take a look.
So right, so what you're saying that it's still פסול according to
תוספות מדרבנן, right?
Yeah yeah, let's not keep on going back to that, but yeah.
Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like this. כתיקנן
לפיגול. Kitiknan l'pigul. One minute. והא מדקתני Ve-ha mide-katani לפיכך נתנן כולן
כתיקנן le-fichach nasan kulan kitiknan ועשאן שלא כתיקנן ve-asan shelo kitiknan פסול
ואין בו כרת, pasul ve-ein bo kareit,
מכלל דתיקנה להכשרו הוא דאתא. mikhlal de-sikna l'hakhshero hu de-asa. So the
גמרא Gemara makes it sound like no, no, no, the word כתיקנה
kitikna makes it sound like כתיקנה kitikna is going to make it
better, not כתיקנה kitikna is going to make it worse. It's not
exactly clear how it's being מדייק medayak that from the grammar of
the משנה. Mishna. Certainly I think we could all admit that that
is correct. What exactly the דיוק diyuk is is not clear, but
anyway let's see what the גמרא's answer is. אמר רבא Amar Rava
מאי שלא כתיקנן mai shelo kitiknan חוץ למקומו. chutz limkomo Okay, so
שלא כתיקנן shelo kitiknan does not mean שתיקה. shtika. רש"י basically says
is is that the phrase שלא כתיקנן shelo kitiknan suggests not just
the absence of a פיגול pigul thought, which is the way you're
reading it, the phrase שלא כתיקנן shelo kitiknan makes it sound like
there's something that's actively bad about this. So if you're reading what's
bad is פיגול pigul and these mean שתיקה, shtika that's a reading
that works. But you're saying this means פיגול, pigul this can't just
mean שתיקה. shtika שלא כתיקנן Shelo kitiknan sounds like it's a bad
מחשבה. So the גמרא says okay, I'll make it a bad מחשבה.
I'll make it a חוץ למקומו chutz limkomo מחשבה. Still works. Okay,
so I'm going to read it the same way and I'm going
to say כתיקנן kitiknan means פיגול, pigul שלא כתיקנן shelo kitiknan you're
saying it has to mean something bad, not just the absence of
something good, fine, that'll be a חוץ למקומו chutz limkomo. thought, but
still I'm going to read it this way and I'm going to
read it according to the רבנן Rabbanan and the reason it's פסול
is because you don't have פיגול pigul by all four thoughts. Okay,
מאי שלא כתיקנן mai shelo kitiknan חוץ למקומו. chutz limkomo רב אשי
אמר Rav Ashi amar שלא לשמו. shelo lishmo Another way that it
could be bad. Okay, it's חוץ למקומו chutz limkomo, or it's שלא
shelo. לשמו because remember we're talking about a חטאת. Okay, but anyway
and therefore it's פסול and not פיגול. pigul But the problem is
if that's how you're reading this phrase then the reason you would
think that it would be פסול is not because that you need
פיגול pigul by all four. You if this is going to be
something actively bad you'll say that's why it's not פיגול pigul because
we know by פיגול pigul if you mess up during another stage
you prevent it from being פיגול. pigul So that's very distracting. The
גמרא says I refuse to read שלא כתיקנה shelo kitikna like it
just means שתיקה. And if it actively means something bad then it's
completely misleading as to what the issue here is because for you
the issue is that you don't have פיגול pigul by all four
stages not that you have something actively bad here. Okay, so the
גמרא says that's going to be the גמרא's question. מכלל דכי
לא עביד ליה חוץ למקומו ושלא לשמו מחייב? Mikhlal de-chi lo avid
leh chutz limkomo u-shelo lishmo michayev? So are you but no that
makes it sound like that if this was שתיקה you'd be חייב
chayav and according to you if it's שתיקה it's also not פיגול
pigul? because it's not all four. So the גמרא's answer is איידי
דתני רישא פיגול וחייבין עליו כרת תני נמי סיפא פסול ואין בו
כרת. Aidi de-tani reisha pigul ve-chayavin alav kareit tani nami seifa pasul
ve-ein bo kareit. So you might remember that all of this is
by the inner חטאת, right? But by the outer חטאת where one
application suffices, right? The הלכה halachah is if you did number if
you did application number one if this is the outer חטאת where
one suffices if you did one with פיגול pigul and you did
two through four with חוץ למקומו, chutz limkomo right, the הלכה halachah
is פיגול pigul
because it ends by one. If you did one חוץ למקומו chutz
limkomo
and two through four with פיגול pigul the הלכה halachah here is
פסול. Right and that's because here it ends with application number one.
So when we dealt with the outer חטאת we were dealing with
חוץ למקומו chutz limkomo and we were saying because here actually right
it's חוץ למקומו chutz limkomo if it comes first it's פסול if
it comes later it's פיגול pigul. so that was the form here
פיגול pigul some of the thoughts were פיגול pigul, and some were
the חוץ למקומו chutz limkomo, thoughts. So when we get up here
to the inner חטאת we're also going to talk about פיגול pigul
and חוץ למקומו, chutz limkomo but אין הכי נמי ein hachi nami
you're really right even if you were to take out the חוץ
למקומו here this would not be פיגול pigul because it was not
all four parts of the stage. Anyway it is a very דחוק
dachuk read of the משנה Mishna to read that
כתיקנן kitiknan means
פיגול pigul, שלא. I could read it like the רבנן Rabbanan just
by saying that this is not implying order, that this is just
saying אין מפגלין בחצי מתיר. ein mefaglin bechatzi matir. If three out
of the four were done right and one out of the four
was done incorrectly, and I don't care which one out of the
four, right? Then אין מפגלין בחצי מתיר ein mefaglin bechatzi matir and
it's okay. So the all of this issue is because we're insisting
on reading this as if it's sort of saying telling us something
about the order, which is not the פשט of the משנה. Anyway,
that's his claim. His claim is that for רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir
it's not about אין מפגלין בחצי מתיר, ein mefaglin bechatzi matir, מפגלין
בחצי מתיר, mefaglin bechatzi matir it's about that the פיגול pigul thought
comes first. So let's just read one more line to get beyond
this weird דיוק diyuk from the משנה and get to the גמרא
directly dealing with this claim about whether רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir holds
מפגלין בחצי מתיר mefaglin bechatzi matir or not. מיתיבי, Meitivei,
so remember Gloria, when they ask you in מרת Marat what you
learned today, you're going to say I learned whether you're מפגלין בחצי
מתיר mefaglin bechatzi matir or אין מפגלין בחצי מתיר. ein mefaglin bechatzi
matir. And you can have a contest to see who can figure
out what that means. Okay, so whether it's מפגלין בחצי מתיר mefaglin
bechatzi matir? or whether it's כל העושה על דעת ראשונה הוא עושה.
Okay, so מיתיבי, Meitivei, במה דברים אמורים bameh devarim amurim בדמים הניתנים
על מזבח החיצון. bedamim hanitanim al mizbe'ach hachitzon. Now when is this
true? Okay, that one application makes פיגול? pigul By the outer חטאת.
That the first application makes פיגול pigul. because it's all about that
first application. Okay, אבל top of מב עמוד א, mem bais amud
aleph, בדמים הניתנים על המזבח הפנימי, bedamim hanitanim al hamizbe'ach hapnimi,
כגון ארבעים ושלוש שיום הכיפורים. arba'im veshalosh sheyom hakippurim. Now they did
the math for you. There are forty-three applications of blood on יום
כיפור. Yom Kippur I erased the whole יום כיפור Yom Kippur? thing,
but how does that work out? Here, because what did you do
by יום כיפור?
Yom Kippur, You did seven
plus one on the כפורת kapporet
and seven plus one on the פרוכת. parochet. Okay, and you did
that, so that's eight plus eight and you did that times two
because you did that both for the פר and the שעיר. So
that's sixteen. Then you mixed the bloods together. Okay, then you mix
them all together and then with one thing you go ahead and
you do seven on the top of the מזבח mizbe'ach and four
on the corners,
so that's eleven. Wait a minute.
No, you have more than that. You have thirty-two from the top
because
each
of them is times two. The seven plus on the כפורת kapporet
times two and then you have thirty-two. Right.
Thank you. Okay, and then you have eleven and therefore you have
forty-three applications of blood.
Okay, now אבל דמים הניתנים על המזבח הפנימי כגון ארבעים ושלוש שיום
הכיפורים aval damim hanitanim al hamizbe'ach hapnimi kegon arba'im veshalosh sheyom hakippurim
ואחת עשרה שפר כהן המשיח ואחת עשרה שפר העלם דבר של ציבור,
ve'achas esrei shepar kohen hamashiach ve'achas esrei shepar helam davar shel tzibbur,
what we just got through, the seven plus the four of those.
In those cases, since all of them are necessary,
פיגל בין בראשונה בין בשנייה בין בשלישית, pigel bein berishona bein beshniya
bein beshlishis, whether you have a פיגול pigul. in the one or
two or three, any type of any one of those things where
all of them are necessary, רבי מאיר אומר פיגול וחייבין עליו כרת.
Rabbi Meir omer pigul vechayavin alav kares. There you go. You can't
be more explicit. You have a פיגול thought at any one of
those applications. רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says that's enough to create פיגול.
וחכמים אומרים אין בו כרת עד שיפגל בכל המתיר. vechachamim omrim ein
bo kares ad sheyefagel bechol hamatir. You have to have פיגול with
all of the applications of blood, all of those that are necessary.
How could you be more explicit that רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir, saying
מפגלין בחצי מתיר? m'faglin bechatzi matir, First of all, the way the
רבנן Rabbanan express their position is יפגל בכל המתיר, yefagel bechol hamatir,
but number two is רבי מאיר says, so implicitly רבי מאיר disagrees.
But number two is that רבי מאיר says any one of those
stages. Okay, so I'll just read you the one sentence answer and
we'll pick up with this tomorrow. It's going to be again a
real דחוק dachuk read.
So the גמרא says קתני מיהת פיגל בין בראשונה בין בשנייה בין
בשלישית ופליגי katani mihat pigel bein berishona bein beshniya bein beshlishis ufligi
and the point and that's where רבי מאיר debates and says that
it's פיגול, פליגי פיגול. pligi pigul. Okay, anyway, אמר רבי יצחק בר
אבין הכא במאי עסקינן amar Rabbi Yitzchak bar Avin hacha bemai askinan
כגון שפיגל בשחיטה דחד מתיר הוא. kegon shepigel beshchita dechad matir hu.
Oy. So what he is saying is when it says you have
פיגול at any stage here, this is such a דחוק dachuk read.
What it means is let's say in the middle of all this
stuff of יום כיפור, you did all these things and then the,
I don't know, and then the, you know, the blood spilled. Okay,
so what do you have to do? So according to one opinion,
שחטו shachtu new cow, get new blood and continue where you left
off or שחטו shachtu new goat. So what he's saying is if
פיגול at any one of these stages you make פיגול, what it
means is no, no, no, it was a scenario where you had
to do a new שחיטה shchita and at that new שחיטה, shchita,
that's when you had a פיגול thought and that's why you made
פיגול in the middle because that was an entire מתיר, which is
like what? Like first of all, if that's really true, would the
Rabbis really disagree? Because then you really were מפגל בכל המתיר and
like that is such a crazy read of the case. רבי מאיר
is talking about any of the applications of blood makes פיגול. So
we will continue with that דחוק dachuk answer tomorrow, but clearly this
ברייתא seems to make very clear that for רבי מאיר, מפגלין בחצי
מתיר, it doesn't matter what stage, any one of the applications can
make פיגול. We'll continue tomorrow.